<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Strange and wonderful news being a true, tho' sad relation of six sea-men. (Belonging to the Margaret of Boston,) who sold themselves to the devil, and were invisibly carry'd away. : With an account of the said ship being sunk under water, where she continued full eleven weeks : all which time, to admiration, the rest of the ship's crew liv'd, and fed upon raw meat, and live fish, that swam over their heads. : The names of three persons, that were (thro' mercy) preserv'd so long under water, were William Davies, (a man very well known to the merchants in London,) Mr. VVilliam Kadner, and Mr. William Bywater. : There was only one boy drowned. : The truth of which strange and miraculous relation, will be attested at Mr. Loyd's coffee house, near the general post-office, in Lombard-Street; where the original letter at large, will be shewn to any person that desires to be further satisfy'd in the truth hereof; : and by several eminent merchants upon the Exchange.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 7 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93981</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5848A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R184679</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">43077654</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 43077654</idno>
            <idno type="VID">151765</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93981)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 151765)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2275:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Strange and wonderful news being a true, tho' sad relation of six sea-men. (Belonging to the Margaret of Boston,) who sold themselves to the devil, and were invisibly carry'd away. : With an account of the said ship being sunk under water, where she continued full eleven weeks : all which time, to admiration, the rest of the ship's crew liv'd, and fed upon raw meat, and live fish, that swam over their heads. : The names of three persons, that were (thro' mercy) preserv'd so long under water, were William Davies, (a man very well known to the merchants in London,) Mr. VVilliam Kadner, and Mr. William Bywater. : There was only one boy drowned. : The truth of which strange and miraculous relation, will be attested at Mr. Loyd's coffee house, near the general post-office, in Lombard-Street; where the original letter at large, will be shewn to any person that desires to be further satisfy'd in the truth hereof; : and by several eminent merchants upon the Exchange.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[1], 2-8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for H. Martyn, in Cornhil,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1700?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Date of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: British Library, London, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Margaret (Ship)</term>
               <term>Ships --  Legends --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:151765:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Strange and Wonderful News.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Being a True, tho' Sad RELATION OF <hi>Six Sea-Men.</hi> (Belonging to the <hi>Margaret</hi> of <hi>Boſton,</hi>) WHO Sold Themſelves to the <hi>Devil, And were Inviſibly Carry'd away.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With an ACCOUNT of the ſaid SHIP being Sunk under Water, where She con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued full <hi>Eleven</hi> Weeks: All which Time, to Admiration, the reſt of the SHIP's Crew Liv'd, and Fed upon Raw Meat, and Live Fiſh, that ſwam over their Heads.</p>
            <p>The Names of the <hi>Three</hi> Perſons, that were (thro' Mercy) Preſerv'd ſo long under wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter, were <hi>William Davies,</hi> (a Man very well known to the Merchants in <hi>London,</hi>) Mr. <hi>William Kadner,</hi> and Mr. <hi>VVilliam Bywater.</hi> There was only <hi>One Boy</hi> Drowned.</p>
            <p>☞ <hi>The Truth of which Strange and Miraculous</hi> RELATION, <hi>will be Atteſted at Mr.</hi> Loyd<hi>'s Coffee Houſe, near the</hi> General Poſt-Office, <hi>in</hi> Lumbard-Street; <hi>where the Original Letter, at large, will be ſhewn to any Perſon, that deſires to be further ſatisfy'd in the Truth hereof; and by ſeveral Eminent Merchants upon the</hi> Exchange.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>H. Marſton,</hi> in <hi>Cornhil.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:151765:2"/>
            <head>A Sad, but True Relation, of <hi>Six Seamen</hi> who Sold themſelves to the <hi>Devil, &amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>THough this following Relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on contains matter of very great Wonder and Amaze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; nevertheleſs it comes to our Hands, confirm'd by that ſuffitient Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony, that we offer it to the Reader as a Narrative of unqueſtion'd Truth and Reputation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By a Letter from <hi>Barbadoes,</hi> of the 23d. of <hi>July</hi> laſt, written by a Perſon of Worth and Credit, in that Iſland, we have this Relation, <hi>viz.</hi> That the <hi>Margaret</hi> from <hi>Boſton,</hi> the 21th. of <hi>December</hi> 95 bound to <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>badoes,</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:151765:2"/>in their Paſſage one of the Saylers at the Helm call'd to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the Veſſel, and told him, <hi>That he could ſteer no longer.</hi> The Maſter asking the reaſon, he replyed, <hi>That he was not well;</hi> and for that cauſe quitted his Poſt; the Maſter taking the Helm, the ſaid Sailor further de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, That there ſtood a Spirit by the Binnacle, that accus'd him of kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling a Woman; a Fault which the Spirit had falſly charg'd him with; for he never committed any ſuch un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manly Crime in his Life. The Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, he ſaid, further told him, That all the Ships Company had ſign'd an Agreement with the Divel, which was us'd as an Argument for him to do the ſame.</p>
            <p>The next day the Fellow fell into ſtrange Deliriums, and talk'd of wonderful Accidents that would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fal the Ship; which were look'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:151765:3"/>as nothing but the wild Notions of his crazed Senſes, the Chimera's of Frenzy. Particularly he ſaid, <hi>That the Spirit had brought a Boat to fetch him away;</hi> with other ridiculous idle Diſcourſe of the ſame Nature.</p>
            <p>Upon the 17th. of <hi>January</hi> in the Latitude of 19 about 9 at Night, a ſmall white Cloud aroſe, without a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Rain, or extraordinary Wind, which preſently falling upon the ſhip preſſed her down with that ſtrange and indeed ſupernatural Weight and force that the Hatches flew out, and the whole Ship was under Water, by which unhappy Accident, the Boy was waſh'd off and drowned.</p>
            <p>But here to begin the more Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous Part of my Narrative, the Ship continued under Water for E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leven Weeks; a thing that ſtruck (as may be well imagined) an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:151765:3"/>Conſternation and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion through the Marriners, from ſeveral ſtrange Arguments of their Aſtoniſhment. <hi>Firſt,</hi> That the Ship ſhould be wholly immerged under Water, and yet not ſunk downright to the bottom. <hi>Secondly,</hi> That tho' they were apparently thus intirely under Water, yet the Ship was not wholly filled with Water, but that they had Air enough to breath in, by which means they continued a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live; feeding all this while, upon raw meat, and freſh Fiſh which came ſwimming over the Veſſel, and ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of which they Caught and Eat. Their Lodging was on Boards pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced athwart the Rail near the Taffrel covered with a Sail. The men were always wet which, in ſo long a time, made that Impreſſion upon them that their Fleſh on their Bodies was gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and raw.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:151765:4"/>
            <p>But what was the moſt diſmal part of all, Six of the Ship's Crew upon the ſinking of the Veſſel under wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, were frighted with <hi>Infernal Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits;</hi> and about 12 the firſt Night were carried away inviſibly, leaving no more then 4 Perſons alive behind them; which indeed gave ſome lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Credit to what the fore mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Sailor at the Helm had declared in his <hi>Deliriums.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>After this 11 Weeks Immurement theſe wondrous watry Walls, for ſo I may juſtly call it, the Ship recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it ſelf above Water again; and the firſt Land they could diſcover was the Iſland <hi>Diſſiado,</hi> which, with ſo few Hands left, they could not fetch up, by reaſon of a ſtrong <hi>Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thern</hi> Current that bore againſt 'em. The next was <hi>Grand-Terra,</hi> where they met with the ſame Diſapoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:151765:4"/>But on the 5th. of <hi>April</hi> they run themſelves on Shore upon <hi>Guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delupo;</hi> where the <hi>French</hi> Treated them very kindly, not as Priſoners, but as Men in Diſtreſs.</p>
            <p>The names of the Three <hi>Seamen</hi> left Alive are <hi>William Davis</hi> Maſter (a Man very well known in <hi>London</hi> amongſt the <hi>Berbadoes</hi> Merchants) <hi>William Cadner,</hi> and <hi>William Bywater.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Not only the Original Letter, and the whole Relation, at large; is to be ſeen at Mr.</hi> Lloyd<hi>'s Coffee-houſe in</hi> Lumbard-ſtreet, <hi>but likewiſe ſeveral Perſons are to be heard of, and ſpoken withal upon the</hi> Exchange, <hi>in Atteſtation of the whole Truth herein decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:151765:5"/>
            <p>The Reverend Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> in his Treatiſe of <hi>Spirits,</hi> ſays, <hi>That tho' Hurricanes and Tempeſts have Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Cauſes, yet there is great Reaſon to think they are managed by Spirits:</hi> In Confirmation whereof, he relates many notable Inſtances of his own, particular Deliverances from the Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of moſt Boyſterous Whirlewinds; namely, when the Reapers in <hi>Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſham</hi> Vale, were Hurt, Writhen, and One Killed, ſome Friendly Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er (for ſo he expreſſes it) reſtrain'd the courſe of Gravally Sand, rais'd by a Whirlwind, as it met him in a narrow Lane.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="license">
            <p>
               <hi>Licenſed according to Order.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
